All right, today's דף daf is כד chaf dalet and we pick
up already halfway into כד עמוד א. chaf dalet amud aleph. To
remember, to remind you what we were discussing yesterday,
we had a debate between רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda whether you could use an animal for a wall of
a סוכה. sukkah. And the גמרא Gemara framed the debate that according
to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, at least according to אביי, Abaye, we
were concerned that the animal would die. According to רב זירא, Rav
Zeira, we were concerned the animal would run away, it's a type
of a גזירה. gezeirah. And then the גמרא Gemara had a question
and then their סוכה, sukkah, the wall would shrink to less than
עשרה טפחים. asara tefachim. And then the גמרא Gemara had a question
that how could אביי Abaye make this a debate of רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda whether you would be concerned
if it would die if אביי Abaye himself had רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda have the reverse positions about the
debate? Because there's a משנה mishnah
that basically says that if a woman is married to a כהן
kohen and he's not and he leaves on a trip, she can
assume he's still alive, so we're not concerned he's he died and
therefore she can no longer eat תרומה. terumah. And on the other
hand, if he gives her a גט get and says, 'this is
your גט get a minute before I die,' that she can't eat
תרומה. terumah. So what is it? Are we concerned he'll die or
are we not concerned he'll die? And אביי Abaye said that this
is really a debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, but he quoted a משנה, mishnah, but then linked it
in to a משנה mishnah of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, which is the reverse of our debate of רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda about the animal dying.
Why? This was a point about taking תרומות ומעשרות terumos u-ma'asros from
grain bought from כותים, Chutim, Samaritans, and you want to take it
and it's already בין השמשות, bein hashmashos,
and you can't actually directly be מפריש mafrish תרומות ומעשרות terumos u-ma'asros
in בין השמשות. bein hashmashos. So what do you do? You say,
'I'm taking it, but I'm taking תרומות terumos and מעשרות ma'asros etc.
on the amount on the things that I will designate after שבת.'
Shabbos. And that's the idea of ברירה. breira. Based on what you
are going to designate later שבת, Shabbos, that will retroactively mean what
you will be doing here. I want to clarify, I don't think
I said it precisely correct yesterday, two important points. Number one is
is that we actually are assuming that the grain bought from the
כותים Chutim is definitely טבל, tevel, meaning it's not a ספק, safek,
it's not דמאי, demai, it is definitely טבל. tevel. Thank you. And
but nevertheless we allow you to take it on בין השמשות, bein
hashmashos, we would not allow you to take normal טבל tevel on
בין השמשות bein hashmashos because you are doing it in a way
where you are not actually designating it right now. You're taking it
without designating it because you're doing this trick, we let you do
it בין השמשות. bein hashmashos.
Why can't you designate it? A גזירה gezeirah because of שבת?
Shabbos? No, you're not allowed to be מפריש mafrish תרומות ומעשרות terumos
u-ma'asros from טבל tevel from ודאי טבל vadai tevel on שבת Shabbos
or even בין השמשות bein hashmashos because it looks like you're fixing
something, you're fixing the grain. But we'll let you do it in
this sort of more, you know, more
כלי אחר יד, kli acher yad, yeah,
as it were, right, not as much of a direct designation.
There was a debate as to whether it's a גזירה שמא? gezeirah
shema?
No, no, בין השמשות bein hashmashos is a ספק שבת, safek Shabbos,
ספק יום ספק לילה. safek yom safek layla. So רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says that you're allowed to and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
you're not allowed to. And it sounds like that's the debate of
whether something will die, but in the reverse, that רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir is not concerned the barrels will break, I'm sorry, רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir is not concerned the barrels will break and רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda won't let you do it because he's concerned the barrels
will break, and when it becomes מוצאי שבת, Motzaei Shabbos, it would
you won't have something to take and you won't retroactively be any
good. So that's the question about, you know, there we have a
debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, will
something die? Will the barrel break? But it is the reverse of
what אביי Abaye wanted to say. אביי Abaye wanted to say רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir is afraid the animal will die, רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda isn't, and here we have רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir being okay
with this trick of taking the wine and not being afraid what
will happen if the wine flask will break and רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda is afraid what will happen if the wine flask will break.
So that's sort of where we left off. So we'll pick up,
although we had gotten halfway through the דף, daf, we'll reread it
just to ground us again. So we'll pick up from the top
of כד עמוד א. chaf dalet amud aleph. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this, the very last line on the, the very last
word on the first line of כד עמוד א. chaf dalet amud
aleph. So with this issue of the wine and the flask breaking,
as again, it sounds like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is not concerned
and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is concerned. So the גמרא Gemara says
איפוך, eippoch, reverse it, meaning not reverse who says what in the
משנה mishnah about the wine, but when אביי Abaye was saying the
question about will the wife of the כהן, kohen, will the wife
of the כהן, kohen, will the כהן kohen die and can the
wife continue to eat is a debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
and רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, it's not this רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda about the wine. It's רבי מאיר חייש
למיעוטא Rabbi Meir chish l'miyuta and רבי יהודה לא חייש למיעוטא. Rabbi
Yehuda lo chish l'miyuta. It's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda of our case about the animal that's the wall. רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir is concerned the animal will die, רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda is not concerned, and that's the same debate of whether the
wife of the כהן kohen can continue to eat when the כהן
kohen gives her a גט. get. By the animal, by the כהן,
Kohen, רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda is not concerned about death. דתניא, D'tanya,
and this is the
debate what we said before. עשאו
לבהמה דופן לסוכה רבי מאיר פוסל רבי יהודה מכשיר. Asa'o lebehema dofen
lesukkah Rebbi Meir posel Rebbi Yehuda machshir.
Fine. So now we get that the issue about can the כהן's
Kohen wife eat the תרומה, trumah, are we afraid the כהן Kohen
will die, depends on the debate of רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir and
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda by the animal. Are we afraid the animal
will die? But now we have to say, but then how does
it fit into the wine case? קשיא דרבי מאיר אד רבי מאיר.
Kashya d'Rebbi Meir ad Rebbi Meir. So now רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
who's not concerned the animal will die, not concerned that the כהן
Kohen will die, I'm sorry, רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir who is concerned
the animal will die, is concerned that the כהן Kohen will die,
why is he not concerned about the wine? שמא יבקע הנוד.
Shema
yibake'a hano'd.
אמר לך רבי מאיר מיתה שכיחא בקיעת הנוד לא שכיחא. Amar lach
Rebbi Meir, misa sh'chicha, b'kiyass hanod lo sh'chicha.
Death is more common than a flask breaking. That's a not a
very optimistic view on life. ואפשר דמצי ליה לשומר. V'efshar d'matzei lei
lishomer. You know, you can have somebody watch a flask not to
break. Who's going to protect somebody from dying? People do die. Okay,
so yes, רבי מאיר's Rebbi Meir concerned the animal will die and
the כהן Kohen will die, he's not concerned about the flask. קשיא
דרבי יהודה אד רבי יהודה. Kashya d'Rebbi Yehuda ad Rebbi Yehuda. How
'bout רבי יהודה? Rebbi Yehuda? If רבי יהודה's Rebbi Yehuda not concerned
the animal will die, not concerned the כהן Kohen will die, why
is he concerned that the flask will break? So the גמרא Gemara
says no, טעמא דרבי יהודה לאו משום דחייש לבקיעת הנוד. Ta'ama d'Rebbi
Yehuda lav mishum d'chaish l'vkiyas hanod. רבי יהודה's Rebbi Yehuda concern is
not about the flask will break, he's not concerned about those things.
And as presumably as we said before, the flask breaking is a
lesser concern than dying, and he's not even... and he's not concerned
that people will die, animals die, flasks will break, he's not concerned
with any of that. So רבי יהודה לאו אלא משום דלית ליה
ברירה. Rebbi Yehuda lav ella mishum d'leis lei breira.
He just doesn't like doing... he doesn't allow you to do it
because he doesn't believe that what you do מוצאי שבת motzei Shabbos
can retroactively define what you did בין השמשות. bein hashmashos. But he's
not at all concerned about things breaking. So גמרא Gemara says, ולא
חייש רבי יהודה לבקיעת הנוד? V'lo chaish Rebbi Yehuda l'vkiyas hanod? You're
telling me he's not concerned the flask will break? והא מדתני סיפא
אמרו לו לרבי מאיר, Veha midtani seifa amru lo l'Rebbi Meir, they,
רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, רבי יוסי, Rebbi Yosi, and רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon said to רבי מאיר: Rebbi Meir: אי אתה מודה שמא יבקע
הנוד ונמצא זה שותה טבלים למפרע? Iy atta modeh shema yibaka hanod
v'nimtza zeh shoteh tevalim l'mafrea?
Aren't you רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir concerned the flask will break and
then retroactively he'll have drunk טבל? tevel? So there will never be
any wine after שבת Shabbos and the whole thing won't work out
retroactively because
it was broken in the meantime.
Yes, exactly. And if it's not around מוצאי שבת motzei Shabbos then
it's not there to designate. Right. ואמר להו V'amar la'u he said
back to them, לכשיבקע. L'chsheyibaka. I'll worry about it when it happens.
Meaning I'm not worried about it. So you see, מכלל דחייש רבי
יהודה לבקיעת הנוד. Miklal d'chaish Rebbi Yehuda l'vkiyas hanod. רבי יהודה Rebbi
Yehuda is concerned that the flask will break. So how can you
say he's not concerned the animal will die, he's not concerned the
כהן Kohen will die, he's concerned the flask will break? So התם,
Hatam, no, the גמרא Gemara says no. רבי יהודה הוא דקאמר לרבי
מאיר. Rebbi Yehuda hu d'ka'amar l'Rebbi Meir. That's רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
answering רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir on his own terms. לדידי, L'didi, as
far as I'm concerned, לית ליה ברירה. leis lei breira. I reject
this whole idea of this trick where now it's תרומות ומעשרות trumos
u'ma'asros based on what I'm going to say מוצאי שבת. motzei Shabbos.
I don't buy this whole ברירה breira thing. Okay. Fine. אלא לדידך
דאית ברירה, Ella l'didach d'is breira, you, we have a fundamental agreement.
You believe you can do this ברירה, breira, you can designate something
later, retroactively it means what you're saying now. You still shouldn't allow
this case. אי אתה מודה דשמא יבקע הנוד? Iy atta modeh d'shema
yibaka hanod? Aren't... you should at least concede that you can't do
it here because the flask might break. ואמר ליה לכשיבקע. V'amar lei,
l'chsheyibaka. No,
I'm not worried about it. Okay. So what we have is the
issue by the wine is not a general concern of are you
concerned about death. The wine presumably is more able to be protected
against that, and there's other issues to raise there, ברירה breira issues,
but it's not the concern of death. And we're saying that the
issue about the animal for the wall of the סוכה, Sukkah, the
concern about death, and that maps onto the issue about whether the
כהן's Kohen wife can continue to eat תרומה. trumah. So the גמרא
Gemara says the following. ולא חייש רבי יהודה למיתה? V'lo chaish Rebbi
Yehuda l'misa? One minute. How can you say רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
isn't concerned about death? והא תנן, Veha tnan, we taught in the
משנה, Mishnah, רבי יהודה אומר, Rebbi Yehuda omer, the first משנה Mishnah
in יומא: Yoma: אף אשה אחרת מתקינין לו שמא תמות אשתו. Af
isha acheres matkinin lo shema tamus ishto. Right?
Don't remember that whole thing? He says you have to have a
backup wife, maybe his wife will die. So you see רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda is concerned about death. So actually all the sources so
far line up that רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda is concerned about death.
He doesn't like the wine thing cause the wine flask will break.
He could be the one that says that the כהן's Kohen wife
can't continue to eat, right? And now you've got him being the
one that
wants a backup wife.
Concerned about death all the probability.
So if you explain the animal, the issue of the animal of
the wall to a סוכה Sukkah in a different way, then it
actually works out much better because then all the רבי יהודהs Rebbi
Yehuda sort of line up. But but now we're trying to assert
that the issue about the animal is about death. So don't you
see that רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda is concerned? How could you say
he's not concerned? So the גמרא Gemara says, הא אתמר עלה אמר
רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע מה לא עשו בכפרה? Ha'itmar alah, amar
Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua, mah lo asu b'chapara? No, that's... you
know, come on, it's כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, it's יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. We'll make a lot of crazy demands there. Gotta stand seven
days beforehand, and you have to
have the
פר. par. Okay. So, now what we have done is we've argued
that the issue about the animal according to אביי Abaye is an
issue of are you concerned about death or not, although that led
to problems because a number of רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda seem to
be concerned about death, and according to this explanation he's not. We
managed to somehow resolve them. He's not really concerned about the flask
breaking. He's just arguing רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir לשיטתו. le-shitato. He's not
really concerned about people dying. It's just a יום כיפור Yom Kippur
issue. Fine. That's the way we're saying it right now. I should,
by the way, before we continue to a new approach about the
animal, say something about this issue about the
כהן's Kohen wife being concerned that her husband will die. The גמרא
Gemara here has made it a debate, are you concerned about death
or not. But the גמרא Gemara elsewhere makes it a more interesting
conceptual difference. The two scenarios were: one was that the כהן Kohen
went on a trip and his wife can continue to eat תרומה
Terumah assuming that he's alive. The other is the כהן Kohen gives
a גט get to his wife and says, "This גט get will
take effect a minute before I die," and she can't eat because
every minute she has to be concerned this is the minute before
he dies. So, the way the גמרא's Gemara explained this is a
debate, are you concerned about death or not? But there's actually another
גמרא Gemara that says no, it doesn't have to be that. There's
a difference between the two cases. And this is a very interesting
but important difference. It says שמא מת, Shema met, לא חיישינן. lo
chashinan. שמא ימות, Shema yamut, חיישינן. chashinan. Right? In one case, can
I eat תרומה? Terumah? My husband is on a trip. Is he
alive now or is he dead? I don't have to be concerned
that he's dead. He left alive. I can assume, I can assume
that he's still alive. I don't have to assume that this minute
he's dead. But if my husband gives me a גט get and
says this will take effect a minute before I die, so I'm
not, for it to be a problem I don't have to say
right now he's dead. What do I have to say? Maybe he
will die a minute from now. So, even though I know he's
alive, and therefore I can assume he's still alive, that doesn't tell
me that he's going to be alive a minute from now. A
minute from now I'll be able to say he's still alive. But
the status quo that he's alive, you don't understand it, Charlie?
I understand it, I just—It
doesn't work in terms of probability. Yeah. Okay, it's not a mathematical
issue. It's a status quo issue.
What's the motivation for saying a minute before I die? I understand
that. It's just this גט get takes effect a minute before I
die.
Oh, so that he's not left to the חיוב chiyuv of יבום
yibbum with the brother.
Oh, that's right. Okay.
So, right, meaning if it's an assertion of facts, then we assume
the facts are the way we saw them last, that he's still
alive. If it's a question about what will happen, well, what the
facts are right now doesn't predict the future, and he might die
a minute from now. So, that's a very nice distinction the גמרא
Gemara makes elsewhere, not here. Here it makes it a concern about
death and makes a distinction between, and makes it a debate, are
we concerned about death or not. Yes.
Great question. What's the difference between ברירה breira as we've been explaining
it and, for example, the following: הרי זו מקודשת על מנת שאני
אחזור ממדינת הים? harei zu mekudeshet al m'nat she-ani achzor mi-medinat ha-yam?
Right. Right.
So, that's what some of these big תוספות-ists Tosafot are about. Basically
the difference between תנאי tnai and ברירה, breira, although it's promised that
there's one or two גמרות Gemaras that try to conflate the two.
But the difference between a condition and ברירה breira is that the
condition is you're saying, I'm definite, all the components about what
make up the act, this is the גט get or this is
the כסף קידושין, kesef kiddushin, you are the woman I'm giving it
to, all of those things are defined. What you are making conditional
is whether it will or won't take effect based on whether a
certain condition is met. As opposed to by ברירה, breira, where it's
more that the very constituent objects themselves are not defined. Which, which
thing goes to you and which thing goes to me will be
determined based on something, based on what I say in the future.
Right? Which, which wine is תרומות ומעשרות Terumot u-Ma'asrot and which wine
is not, the object that I am actually being מפריש mafrish is
not defined in the act. If I say I'm being מפריש mafrish
this wine, this barrel as תרומה, Terumah, but on the condition that
A, B, and C happen, that A happens, but if A doesn't
happen, I מפריש mafrish that barrel, that's not ברירה, breira, that's a
תנאי, tnai, because each act is sort of, the constituent, the constituents
of the act are defined. It's just whether or not it takes
effect is what is being held in abeyance. As opposed to classic
ברירה, breira, where it's the very objects and the constituents of the
act that are not defined, that are not defined. That's like one
way of explaining the difference. Okay? But let's—it's not—it's complicated. It's what
big תוספות Tosafot is about. But there generally is a difference when
you say this should happen on the condition that, that's a תנאי.
tnai. If you say this is, this will happen to the thing
that I designate later, that's ברירה, breira, because the thing you're doing
it is not defined
right now.
In ברירה, breira, do you, when you say
as of
מוצאי שבת, Motzaei Shabbat, does that
mean...
Right, it's as if it's already changed its status before the condition
has become חל. chal.
Right, once the condition is חל, chal, then we look retroactively and
say that that's what took effect when you said it. But that
doesn't make it different from a תנאי. tnai. By a תנאי tnai
I can say this is you know this is your גט get
or this is your קידושין kiddushin as of this minute on the
condition that the Mets win the World Series. And then if and
when the Mets ever win the World Series, how long ago was
that happened? Anyway, then retroactively it'll be as of today. So תנאי
tnai also can be retroactive. That's not the difference.
That was שוה בשוה. shaveh b'shaveh.
Okay, so anyway right. Okay, yes.
If a person dies, then would the wife automatically consider that she
can remarry?
So when the person dies in that case of the גט get
with the כהן's Kohen wife,
in other words, I'm asking why is it- you said it was
because of יבמה. yevamah. Right, but I'm wondering if it might also
be because that way she's free to remarry?
No, she'd be free to remarry anyway because she's a widow.
Once once he's died.
Right, and anyway the גט get makes her אסורה asurah to marry
a כהן Kohen so makes it more problematic. Maybe that's why he's
doing it, he wants to prevent her from marrying a כהן. Kohen.
Okay, anyway, so let's take a look. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. בין למאן דאמר שמא תמות
בין למאן דאמר שמא תברח. Bein l'man d'amar shema tamut bein l'man
d'amar shema tivrach. So now the way we frame the issue about
the animal for the wall, whether it's a concern of death according
to אביי Abaye or concern of running away according to רבי זירא.
Rabbi Zeira. מדאורייתא מחיצה מעליא היא. Mide'oraisa mechitza ma'alya hi. Biblically it's
a good מחיצה. mechitza. ורבנן הוא דגזרו בה. Verabbanan hu d'gazru bah.
It's a rabbinic concern. That's what we said the other day. Right,
I wanted to say oh well maybe because it might die it's
not considered that it's going to be a you know it's going
to be a like a like a dwelling
because the wall isn't permanent or the wall is very you know
is not stable. But the גמרא Gemara here frames it very much
in what we've clear all along that the גמרא Gemara was not
seeing it that way. The גמרא Gemara was thinking it as no,
it is כשר, kosher, but we don't let you use it because
it might die, it might run away and then you won't be
paying attention and you won't be יוצא. yotzei. And that's the concern.
Is that the concern the elephant in the room?
Ah, maybe. Okay, so
מדאורייתא מחיצה מעליא היא. Mide'oraisa mechitza ma'alya hi. Biblically it's good. That's
the way they're explaining it. ורבנן הוא דגזרו בה. Verabbanan hu d'gazru
bah. It's a rabbinic concern. אלא מעתה לרבי מאיר דטימאה משום גולל.
Ella me'ata l'Rabbi Meir detime'ah mishum golel. According to that you can
only be מחמיר. machmir. You can say I'm afraid it'll run away,
I'm afraid it'll die, don't use it. But then but how could
we ever be lenient and what if you're trying to use this
thing as a type of a headstone for a grave which sounds
totally bizarre. But the idea is it might be some type of
a marker and that you're waiting until you know until you can
get the headstone actually there. So using it to mark the grave
and there's a הלכה, halacha, it's a big debate what exactly is
a גולל, golel, what exactly is a דופק, dofek, but certain things
that are parts of the grave
are מטמא metamei like the grave.
It's tied there? It's tied there, yeah.
So anyway, so okay, if it's a concern it might die, might
run away, that's a חומרא, chumra, but how would it ever lead
to a קולא? kula? אלמה תנן, Almah tenan, why do we teach
in a משנה: Mishnah: רבי יהודה מטמא משום גולל? Rabbi Yehuda metamei
mishum golel? If you use this animal, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda again
treats animals like any other object and it's to be used as
a wall of a סוכה, Sukkah, it has the טומאה tumah of
a גולל golel of a of a gravestone. ורבי מאיר מטהר. VeRabbi
Meir metaher. ורבי מאיר And Rabbi Meir says that it's טהור. tahor.
So how could that be? Clearly
it's not just a גזירה gezeirah and a stringency, it's an it's
like a more central intrinsic issue that he's disqualifying it. So the
גמרא Gemara says אלא, ella, you know what? Forget everything we've just
said. You're right. We had a whole lovely דף daf yesterday, a
whole question about who holds of death, is it רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, that's not what's going on here. Because
then he would only be מחמיר machmir and we see that he's
also מיקל. meikel. אלא אמר רב אחא בר יעקב. Ella amar Rav
Acha bar Yaakov. קסבר רבי מאיר, Kasavar Rabbi Meir, here's רבי מאיר's
Rabbi Meir's reasoning, his problem with the animal. כל מחיצה שעומדת ברוח
אינה מחיצה. Kol mechitza she'omedes beruach einah mechitza. Any מחיצה mechitza that's
only standing up with wind, with a spirit, with the animating life
spirit of of animals is not a real מחיצה. mechitza. Now one
wonders if this is being a little bit of a pun because
until now we've been saying what's not a good מחיצה mechitza on
סוכה? Sukkah? כל מחיצה שאינה יכולה לעמוד ברוח מצויה. Kol mechitza she'einah
yechola la'amod beruach metzuya. Can't stand up against a wind. And here
we're saying any מחיצה mechitza that is standing ברוח beruach through a
wind, which is how it's imagining the soul, is not a real
מחיצה. mechitza. Now I would have explained that to mean, you know
it's not true based on the next line of גמרא, Gemara, that
basically what you were suggesting yesterday that since it's only standing because
it's alive and it might die, there's a sense of impermanence to
it because it's only because of the fact that it's it needs
to remain alive. Life is what sustains it. Okay, but we're going
to see the גמרא's Gemara's going to translate רוח ruach in a
much more literal way. One minute. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. אמר רב אחא בר יעקב, Amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov, קסבר
רבי מאיר, kasavar Rabbi Meir, כל מחיצה kol mechitza אינה מחיצה. einah
mechitza. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, some say, אמר רב אחא בר יעקב,
amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov, קסבר רבי מאיר, kasavar Rabbi Meir, כל
מחיצה. kol mechitza. שאינה עשויה בידי אדם אינה מחיצה. she'eina asuya biydei
adam eina mechitza. If it’s not made by human beings, it’s not
a מחיצה. mechitza. So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu?
What would be the difference? איכא בינייהו דאוקמה בנוד תפוח. Ika beinaihu
d'ukma b'nod tapuach.
You basically had a wall as an inflatable flask, you used a
big balloon as a wall. Okay, no animals, a big balloon. למאן
דאמר מחיצה עומדת ברוח אינה מחיצה, L'man d'amar mechitza omedet b'ruach eina
mechitza, if Rabbi Meir's concern is that it's something that's standing up
by a wind, הרי עומדת ברוח. harei omedet b'ruach. It's not valid.
So there's nothing to do with life, right? It has to do
somehow with the idea that the fact that it is sustained by
something non-physical, that this is the idea. Whatever it is, רוח ruach
means something like non-physical. We're going to see, we all know air
is physical, but somehow it's not seen as material. So it's basic
sort of, you know, it's like the opposite of the idea of
ממש mamash we have in הלכה, halacha, or it is the idea
of ממש mamash but in the reverse way. Like we say like,
let's say you have some טרף treif ingredient in something that cannot,
this is the gelatin issue, that cannot be tasted, but it gives
form to the object. So maybe that means that it's like gives
part, its identity is imparted by the fact that it gives the
form to the thing, even though it's not the essence of the
thing. Here basically, since the מחיצה mechitza is standing up because of
a non-physical, something that's defined halachically as רוח, ruach, not really physical
and you can't really feel it, right? It's air, it’s the life
spirit, so then this is not really considered a physical מחיצה. mechitza.
It's not a real מחיצה. mechitza. What gives it its standing is
a non-physical thing. It doesn't constitute as a real physical מחיצה. mechitza.
It's quite fascinating. If you want to use a מחיצה mechitza based
on good old fashioned a mat, it can be physical, fine. But
if your basic מחיצה mechitza starts with something sustained by something non-physical,
that's considered to be, that's considered to be, right, not a real
מחיצה. mechitza. That's point one. אבל למאן דאמר אינה עשויה בידי אדם,
Aval l'man d'amar eina asuya biydei adam, but if your concern is
that it's not made by human hands, הרי עשויה בידי אדם, harei
asuya biydei adam, it is made by human hands. So this now
becomes, forget the whole idea of are you concerned about it will
die, it's a more
central question about if something is sustained by like a life spirit,
then it is not, you know, according to Rabbi Meir, that is
not considered to be a fit, you know, an actual, the גמרא
Gemara says it's not a מחיצה, mechitza, but the problem is that
this also has to tie into the issue about the גולל, golo,
about whether it's part of the grave, which is not about it
being a מחיצה, mechitza, but somehow the fact that it's being sustained
by a life spirit and that's part of what gives it its
shape that is necessary for this הלכה, halacha, right? You wouldn't use
a dead animal for a, somehow it's important that it's a standing
animal that you're using it for your grave marker. So if that
is what gives this thing its halachic shape is the fact that
it's being sustained by something non-physical, so for Rabbi Meir that cannot
be const-, that cannot be used. Because we cannot give it its
meaning or its status based on it being sustained through this non-physical
entity. It's a very fascinating idea. The idea by the way that
it have to be done בידי אדם biydei adam
would also mean that Rabbi Meir shouldn't allow you to use for
example a tree for a סוכה, sukkah, right? Which is what we've
had before, you know, that you've had trees for walls. So it's
quite fascinating if that's his issue that he only says it by
בהמה, behema, there's a lot of other things he could disqualify. So
it does seem that the first approach that it’s more about the
life, you know, the animal as a living thing, does seem to
be, you know, more about what's going on here. Yes.
When we say גולל golo and the טומאה, tumah, why did the,
why did the גמרא Gemara say גזירה דרבנן gezeira d'rabbanan said about
the טומאה tumah piece? Why? Because it’s a קולא. kula.
The גולל golo לפי l'fi Rabbi Meir because it's not a גולל
golo it's טהור. tahor. So you can't have a גזירה gezeira leading
for to be טהור. tahor. It had to have a fundamental reason
why it does not have a status, okay, why it can't be
used. Yes.
Other, there wouldn't just be a problem with a tree but you
couldn't use a natural geological feature.
Oh,
that's a good point too. Can you use like a, can you
use a rock?
Side of a rock, yeah.
It's very hard to understand the אינה עשויה בידי אדם eina asuya
biydei adam because you would be have to right be be eliminating,
you know, many many more things. So I don't know, the more
logical thing I, you know, to fit it into the focus on
the animal is this concept of עומדת ברוח. omedet b'ruach. You know,
it's an interesting but they tell kids how to do this science
experiments to show that air has weight because kids don't believe, you
know, you can't believe that air has weight, it's like invisible it's
not real. So what you do is you take a balloon and
you blow it up and you take another same balloon unblown up
and you put it on a balance scale and you see that
the blown up balloon, right, weighs more. So it's a nice little,
you know, way of demonstrating air has weight. But for the גמרא
Gemara it's all רוח, ruach, it's not really real, you can't feel
it. What?
How does that work? There's no more air than there was before.
No, there's no, because there's more air in the balloon. A blown
up balloon has this amount of air where an unblown balloon only
has like the thin amount of air that's inside.
And the balloon with air is heavier than air therefore it puts
weight on the balance on the scale. But why?
Your question
is isn't there air above the scale that's with the unblown balloon
there's also the same amount of air around
it.
Right, but that... That just taken out because the air pressure is
the same in all directions.
We can talk about this later.
Okay, fine. Yet another מחלוקת machlokes here. It does work though, you
could try it. Okay. אמר מר, Amar Mar,
so now the last point is that we've got רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir figured out. Now we're going to look at רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose who applies it also to a גט. get. אמר מר, Amar
Mar, שמשמיה דרבי יוסי הגלילי אמרו, she-mishmeih de'Rabbi Yose HaGlili amru, so
in the name of רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili they said,
going back to this ברייתא, braisa, אף אין כותבין עליו גיטי נשים.
af ein koshvin alav gitei nashim.
You can't write a גט get on an animal. Now
presumably רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir wouldn't have a problem with this because
the animal, whether alive or dead, you could write a גט get
on it, right? So it's not so even if he doesn't want
to even if he wants to discount the fact that it's alive,
you can't that can't be part of its identity, but this would
it matter? So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir wouldn't have a problem of
writing a גט. get. But רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili has
a problem of writing a גט. get. Well, we have to figure
out why is that? מאי טעמא דרבי יוסי הגלילי? Mai ta'ama de'Rabbi
Yose HaGlili? What's his reasoning? דתניא ששנה ברייתא, De-tanya she-shana baraisa, ספר,
sefer, it says וכתב לה ספר כריתות, ve-kasav lah sefer krisus, and
he shall write her a bill of divorce, a book of divorce.
אין לי אלא ספר, Ein li ela sefer, I only know you
can write it in a ספר, sefer, which would mean like a
classic ספר sefer like with a
קלף. klaf. מניין לרבות כל דבר? Minayin lerabbos kol davar? How do
I know you can write on things other than a קלף? klaf?
תלמוד לומר וכתב, Talmud lomar ve-kasav, he shall write it, וכתב לה
מכל מקום. ve-kasav lah mikol makom. It's
you know it's not limited to a ספר, sefer, וכתב לה ve-kasav
lah is more general. So אם כן מה תלמוד לומר ספר? im
ken mah talmud lomar sefer? So then what's ספר sefer doing which
seems to limit it to only like a קלף? klaf? לומר לך,
Lomar lach, to tell you, מה ספר דבר שאין בו רוח חיים
ואינו אוכל, mah sefer davar she-ein bo ruach chayim ve-eino ochel, the
same way a book is something that's not alive and isn't food,
אף כל דבר שאין בו רוח חיים ואינו אוכל, af kol davar
she-ein bo ruach chayim ve-eino ochel, so also it has to be
not alive and not food. You could write a גט get on
anything except something that's not alive and not food. Now, you know,
if I would have, you know, said it has to be like
a book, why or like a קלף, klaf, you know, why would
you pick of all the things those two characteristics, not food and
not alive? I mean, okay, you do see that those are pretty
different in the sense of like an inanimate, you know, piece of
קלף, klaf, but you could have picked other characteristics. So תוספות Tosafos
says, if you take a look at a very important תוספות, Tosafos,
he says מה ספר שאין בו רוח חיים, mah sefer she-ein bo
ruach chayim, so he says, you know, always when the גמרא Gemara
sort of says it has to be like X, how does it
know which characteristic to identify as the salient ones? So the last
line of the תוספות Tosafos is בכל אחד כפי מה שדומה לחכמים
ענין הראוי לו. be-chol echad kefi mah she-domeh la-chachamim inyan ha-ra'uy lo.
Whenever we have to say like it has to be like X
based on the word in a פסוק, pasuk, כלל ופרט וכלל, klal
u-ferat u-klal, anything like the פרט, prat, anything like this, to identify
what are the relevant characteristics of that thing that it has to
be similar to, the the you know, the sages make each decision
based on what's appropriate for the context. So, you know, there's no
way a priori that we're going to prove these are the two
salient characteristics. Their assessment of what most is like a ספר sefer
and most is relevant for the גט get context is something inanimate
and not food. I don't know not food, but food maybe could
be easily consumed and destroyed and so on.
In this parchment, I
know those two characteristics are true about parchment, but there's ten other
characteristics that are true about parchment. Why do we pick those two
that have to be similar to? Why didn't we say it has
to come from an animal? Why didn't we say it has to
be something that's classically used for writing something on? You know, why
why didn't we say I don't know, why don't we say it
has to be thin? You know, who knows which are the relevant
characteristics that we pick out? So obviously you make an assessment, what
are the most relevant characteristics based on your understanding of the context
and, you know, what seems to be most relevant? He says that
in the end is the discretion of the חכמים, Chachamim, how to
interpret the the פסוק pasuk sort of says it has to be
similar. What constitutes the characteristics of similarity? That's what the חכמים Chachamim
decide.
This is a very important statement because yeah so two questions. So
first of all תוספות Tosafos picks out two other areas in the
course of הש"ס.
ha-Shas. Right. Exactly.
So why it's a little strange that he would say well here
and here rather than say everywhere in the גמרא Gemara does this?
Right. But also I was wondering if תוספות Tosafos would say that
they know what the answer is going to be, it's maybe some
kind of מסורה mesorah or something or or you know not exactly
הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai, you know what the answer is
and you have to find a פסוק pasuk or something or
something
to get it from.
Right so that's true, meaning he doesn't say that. He doesn't say
that. He says that the חכמים Chachamim have discretion, right.
Exactly. Well, I will say that that idea, you know, if you
the גמרא Gemara makes it sound like there's a general debate of
academics and it's actually a debate of ראשונים, Rishonim, how many of
these the דרשות drashos are things that we sort of knew the
הלכה halacha and then we were backwards to find a דרשה drashah
that supports it, which isn't exactly the same as אסמכתא asmachta because
אסמכתא asmachta means it's like it's rabbinic. This means like we have
a tradition that this is the meaning of the פסוק, pasuk, but
then we use a hermeneutic to find a way to give it
that to connect it that way. Or do we really not know
what the meaning is and we derive it based on the hermeneutics?
So, you know, some you know there's a debate whether is it
A is it B is it you know some mix of A
and B case by case. You read the גמרא, Gemara, the גמרא
Gemara gives you the sense that we're always deriving it, that we're
never retrofitting it, okay, but that being said
some ראשונים... Rishonim...
Right, and then
re-established.
You do have that in the גמרא. Gemara. That is true. You
do have that sometimes in the גמרא. Gemara. I think החזירה, Achehzira,
you know, they were forgotten בימי יהושע bimei Yehoshua and then they
were restored. That is true. Okay, so now the גמרא, Gemara, but
it's very important at least according to תוספות Tosfos about what it
says about sort of the discretion in תורה שבעל פה. Torah she'be'al
peh. So now we go on. So it says like this. That's
how we learned that it can't be an animal. That's where רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosei ha-Gelili comes from. ורבנן, Ve-rabanan, what would the
Rabbis say back? אי כתוב בספר, Ei kasuv be-sefer, you shall write
in a book כדקאמרת, kedekamarta, then it's like you said, you'd have
to limit the material because it has to be book-like to some
degree. השתא דכתיב ספר, Hashta de-chtiv sefer, it doesn't say write in
a book, it says write a ספר. sefer. ספר Sefer doesn't mean
book here. What does ספר sefer mean? לספירת דברים בעלמא הוא דאתא,
Le-sfiras devarim be'alma hu de-ata, write a ספר כריתות sefer krisus means
a story, write a narrative of divorce. Don't write a book or
write in a book, write something that narrates the fact that this
is a divorce. ורבנן האי וכתב מאי דרשי ביה? Ve-rabanan hai ve-chasav
mai darshi bei? So if that's what ספר sefer means, why do
you need וכתב ve-chasav to be more broad? You know, you don't
need it more broad, you never limited it. It's so funny. Don't
you need וכתב ve-chasav just for the, you know, just for the
פסוק pasuk itself to tell you you have to write? Anyway, so
the גמרא Gemara says הוא מיבעי ליה בכתיבה מתגרשת ואינה מתגרשת
בכסף, hu mibayei lei bi-chsiva misgareshes ve-eina misgareshes be-chesef, that only by
writing and not, you can't give money to effect a divorce. Again,
it's not exactly clear to me what extra word the גמרא Gemara
is learning it out from.
You need
ונתן לה ספר...
ve-nasan lah sefer... ונתנה ספר כריתות ve-nasna sefer krisus because he doesn't
have to be the one to write it. Yeah, okay.
But alright, so anyway וכתב ve-chasav is saying only by writing.
I would have said that it says בכתיבה מתגרשת ואינה מתגרשת בדברים
בעלמא bi-chsiva misgareshes ve-eina misgareshes be-devarim be'alma like oral.
Yeah, but there's no basis to say. But here there's the basis
to say why money would have done it. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka
deitach amina, I would have thought הואיל והוקשה יציאה
להוויה, ho'il ve-huksha yetzia le-havayah, the, it's connected to coming, right? It
says by the divorced wife, it says he divorces his wife ויצאה
והיתה לאיש אחר, ve-yatzah ve-hayesah le-ish acher, she leaves his house and
she becomes to another man. So from there we learn that the
same way, for example, you can divorce with a גט, get, you
can marry with a שטר shtar as well. So maybe I'll also
say the reverse. So מה הויה בכסף, mah havayah be-chesef, if that's
true, then why don't I say the same way you can marry
with money, אף יציאה בכסף, af yetzia be-chesef, get divorced with money?
קא משמע לן, Ka mashma lan, only וכתב, ve-chasav, only by writing.
Okay, so now the Rabbis learn out to never limit, had any
reason to limit the material you're writing on, and וכתב ve-chasav comes
to tell you only by writing, not by something else. רבי יוסי
הגלילי Rabbi Yosei ha-Gelili now, רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosei ha-Gelili who
uses וכתב ve-chasav and ספר sefer to tell you you can write
it on, you can't write it on everything, you can write it
on a wide range of things, but not everything. So האי סבר
מנא ליה, hai savar mana lei, where does he know to exclude
the marriage of, a divorce through money? מספר כריתות נפקא. mi-sefer krisus
nafka. ספר כרת ואין דבר אחר כרת. Sefer karas ve-ein davar acher
karas. No, because the word ספר כריתות sefer krisus and the juxtaposition
says only through a ספר sefer does it effect
severance, divorce, and not through something else. So that's where he learns
you can't do it through money. ואידך, Ve-idach, what do the Rabbis
learn from the juxtaposition of ספר כריתות? sefer krisus? הוא מיבעי ליה
לדבר הכורת בינו לבינה. Hu mibayei lei le-davar ha-kores beino le-veinah. It
has to effect a complete separation. כדתניא, kidetanya, like we taught in
a ברייתא. braisa. הרי זה גיטך על מנת שלא תשתי יין ועל
מנת שלא תלכי לבית אביך, Harei zeh gittech al menas she-lo sishti
yayin ve-al menas she-lo selchi le-veis avich, if he gives her wife
a גט
get
and says this is your גט get on the condition you never
drink wine in your entire life or you never go to your
father's house לעולם, le-olam, אין זה כריתות, ein zeh krisus, it's not
a good גט get because it's a stipulation that for her entire
life keeps her bound to her husband. She never will ever be
absolutely free of her husband, right? Because we'll never know if the
גט get retroactively won't take effect. So therefore that does not, even
if she does fulfill the תנאי, tnai, it's not a גט get
because it's given in a way that never fully effects severance. על
מנת שלשים יום, Al menas she-loshim yom, if he says for thirty
days you can't do these things, הרי זה כריתות, harei zeh krisus,
it is good because after thirty days she will be totally free
of her husband. So that's what they learn from ספר כריתות. sefer
krisus. ואידך, Ve-idach, and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei will say back מכרת
כריתות נפקא. mi-kares krisus nafka. So it could have said ספר כרת,
sefer kares, it says ספר כריתות sefer krisus to tell you two
things: only by a book and a complete severance. ואידך, Ve-idach, and
the חכמים Chachamim will say back כרת כריתות לא דרשי, kares krisus
lo darshi, they're not impressed with the כרת kares and the כריתות,
krisus, it doesn't tell you anything new. So anyway, a whole long
discussion about how we are that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei excludes, we've
excluded animals according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir because when they need
to be standing and their standingness is only created through this spirit,
then it's not considered, we can't give that any הלכה halacha weight,
it's not a real material thing. It's really a fascinating idea of
how much הלכה halacha is, you know, about our concrete physical world
and it's not about our religious reality, if you would. Anyway, that's
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, but the animal not for a גט, get,
why not? It doesn't have to be alive. So that's a... יוסי
הגלילי Yossi HaGlili idea that says it have to be similar in
some ways to the idea of a classic ספר, sefer, classic קלף,
klaf, and the Rabbis don't read it that way. Okay, now we
go on to the next
משנה. Mishnah. העושה סוכתו בין האילנות והאילנות דפנות לה כשרה. Ha'oseh sukato
bein ha'ilanot veha'ilanot defanot lah k'sherah. So here exactly we mentioned a
minute ago the issue about using a tree, something not made by
human hands. Here the משנה Mishnah says it's totally fine. You make
the סוכה sukkah between trees and the trees serve as walls, fine.
Doesn't sound like a big חידוש. chiddush. Let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. אמר רב אחא בר יעקב כל מחיצה שאינה יכולה לעמוד
ברוח מצויה אינה מחיצה. Amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov kol mechitzah she'einah
yecholah la'amod beruach metzuyah einah mechitzah. So this ties back to statements
we had about the סוכה sukkah on the boat, that any מחיצה
mechitzah that cannot stand with a normal wind is not a מחיצה.
mechitzah. There was a question about whether it has to withstand an
abnormal wind, whether it has to be able to withstand the normal
winds on the ocean, but we can all agree that if it
can't withstand a normal wind on the dry land, that that doesn't
count as a מחיצה. mechitzah. Not for סוכה, sukkah, not for שבת,
Shabbos, it can't count as a type of a wall for any
הלכה. halacha. Okay, תנן, t'nan, let's see if this works. העושה סוכתו
בין האילנות והאילנות דפנות לה כשרה, Ha'oseh sukato bein ha'ilanot veha'ilanot defanot
lah k'sherah, you can use the trees as walls. והא קאזיל ואתי,
veha ka'azil ve'atei, one minute, the trees sway in the wind. So
according to you, they're not really, how could they serve as walls?
So even in a normal wind, it wouldn't stay that
way. So הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha b'mai askinan, what are we talking
about? בקישים, b'keshim, a very like old strong tree that it doesn't
sway and its trunk is very solid. So the גמרא Gemara says
ואיכא נופו, ve'ika nofo, but one minute, what about the foliage, the,
what's that called,
what's the word for the canopy of the tree?
Canopy?
Is that the word?
Foliage is fine.
The canopy of a forest, right. Anyway, but what about the whole
head of the tree, right? So doesn't that sway? Now of course,
the point could be who said you're using the head of the
tree? Maybe you're just using the trunk. I mean, for God's sake,
it only has to be ten טפחים. tefachim. How many trees are
so, I mean, I guess how many trees are so low that
they've got foliage like within ten טפחים, tefachim, within
thirty inches? It's got to be a real little sapling. Yeah, but
it says we're talking about an old tree that's solid. So maybe
imagine that you're making it higher up on the trees, you're not
making it the ground level. You make like a platform between trees
higher up, what is it, a willow?
The leaves hang down to the ground.
Oh, okay, so maybe that. Actually, we're going to get a case
just like the willow, just like a willow in a minute. One
minute, let's just see the answer. One minute, where are we, let's
just see the answer. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, but if
the foliage is part of the walls, isn't the foliage going to
sway in the wind? So the גמרא Gemara says ואיכא נופו דאבזייה
בהוצא ודפנא. ve'ika nofo de'avzayei behotza vedafna. No, you use various types
of like of ropes
and cords to keep them in place so it's not going to
sway. It's all very much like we had before, the elephant being
held up with the cords. Here your tree is being held in
a place by these ropes and cords or whatever, so the גמרא
Gemara says אי הכי מאי למימרא, ee hachi mai l'memra, so what's
the חידוש? chiddush? מהו דתימא ניגזר דילמא אתי לאשתמושי באילן, mahu d'teima
nigzar dilma atei l'ishtamushi b'ilan, the חידוש chiddush is we're not concerned
you'll come to use the tree, because remember you can't use a
tree on יום טוב, Yom Tov, that you'll put things on it
or you may break off a branch, קא משמע לן ka mashma
lan we're not concerned. It's not a חידוש chiddush that it's a
wall. Of course it's a wall, you got it all nailed down,
but it is a חידוש chiddush that you're not going, we're not
concerned you'll come to use it. Okay, there was a question?
Yes, what is the definition of a tree? For instance, in במה
מדליקין Bameh Madlikin we have the פשתן pishtan is described as,
right, so it could be that it considers certain types of things
trees that we wouldn't, and therefore it's more concerned about the swaying,
that is true.
Yeah, I was going to say, and you couldn't allow the foliage
to blow anyway because of the סכך. s'chach.
Oh well, but let's say it's totally at the side, meaning you've
got the foliage growing here and
it's, right, okay, but I was just thinking of the tree being
more, tree and,
I imagine if, so here is your tree, right,
and you got another, whoops, you got another tree here, right? So
you sort of build the platform like this, right, and let's say
I don't know, well I don't know, you'd have to figure it
out that the foliage came more like that, yeah, and you did
something like that so it's being used as your walls, right, and
then you put your סכך s'chach here, but the foliage there is
somehow serving as your wall. Anyway, okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
now this by the way is an issue with those canvas סוכות
sukkos that the wind comes and it blows it and it billows
out and it so it's no longer, now the question is, the
question the גמרא Gemara is exploring is how much would it have
to move to not be considered a wall? Presumably, it's only if
after the movement it loses its wall status. So if it still
stays within let's say three טפחים, tefachim, right, and it's still like
it's still anchored at the bottom, and even if it sort of
billows out, it still sort of stays within three טפחים, tefachim, right,
presumably that's okay. Meaning what would be the הלכה halacha if you
have a Presumably, it's only if after the movement it loses its
wall status. So, if it still stays within let's say three טפחים,
tefachim, right, and it's still anchored at the bottom, and even if
it sort of billows out, it still stays within three טפחים, tefachim,
right, presumably that's okay. Meaning what would be the הלכה halacha if
you have a wall actually that looks like
that? Let's say you had a wall that looked like this, the
thing looks when it billows out. Right, let's say you had a
wall like that,
right, just like almost every tent is, right?
So, you know, maybe that is a wall. Who says that a
wall has to be, you know, totally perpendicular? I mean, we had
cases before about something like this, right, the whole פירא, pira, right?
No, but even in our גמרא, Gemara, we had a tipi with
the roof or whatever. You know, so anyway, so is that considered
that it's not עומדת ברוח? omedet beruach?
So, you know, does it have to be like within, you know,
does it have to be like within three טפחים? tefachim? So you
don't know, maybe if it goes out here, you know, it's not
because it's not within three טפחים tefachim of the סכך, s'chach, but
then it comes back up at the top. So, anyway, how much
does it have to blow by the wind in order to be
a problem, in order to not be a wall? Because, you know,
the גמרא Gemara could have said that even if the wind blows
it, if it sort of stays within certain, you know, within the
parameters of the סוכה, sukkah, and sort of everything is sort of
within three טפחים tefachim and so on, you know, maybe it shouldn't
be a problem. So, presumably, it has to blow so much that,
that when it's after the wind is blowing, it can no longer
count as a wall. That's presumably what אינו עומדת eino omedet means.
Okay, so the גמרא's Gemara first answer is that everything is nailed
down. תא שמע, ta shma, come let's try to prove it again.
היה שם אילן או גדר hayah sham ilan o geder או מחיצת
הקנים. o mechitzat hakanim. So this is again the case of the
corners around the well when you're able to draw from the well
and it creates the area around the well as a רשות היחיד.
reshut hayachid. Now, what can you use for those corners? Let's say
that there was a tree at one of the corners or there
was a גדר, geder, which really means like a stone fence, a
stone wall, או מחיצת הקנים, o mechitzat hakanim, or there was a
wall made by reeds. נידון משום דיומד. nidon mishum diyomed. You can
use them to be parts of these corners around the well to
create this רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. So, how can you do that?
Won't the reeds blow in the wind or the tree blow in
the wind? So, הגמרא haGemara says הכא נמי משום דאבדיה בהוצא ודפנא.
hacha nami mishum de'avdye behutza vedafna. Fine, you tied it all down.
Okay, תא שמע, ta shma, let's try again. אילן המיסך על הארץ.
ilan hamaysech al ha'aretz. This is like the willow. If you have
a tree that's overhanging on the ground and creates a canopy with
its sort of overhanging branches. אם אין נופו גבוה מן הארץ שלושה
טפחים, im ein nofo gavoha min ha'aretz sheloshah tefachim, מטלטלין תחתיו. metaltelin
tachtav. If the if the branches are within three טפחים tefachim of
the ground, then it forms a wall and you can carry under
it. Okay, so right, we've got the picture, right? So, you've got
your tree here and its branches are hanging down like this, okay?
Right, those are the branches hanging down. So if the bottom of
the branches here are within three טפחים tefachim of the ground, so
it's like it's connected to the ground and therefore you can use
all of that as walls and assuming you've got it like
on all sides, right, like that, right, then you have a רשות
היחיד reshut hayachid there and you can carry in it. Okay, you
got the idea? So the whole thing is hanging down, it creates
a whole little, you know, a whole canopy below. And if it's
within three טפחים tefachim of the ground, it becomes walls and you
can carry under it. Okay, אמאי? amai? Why? הא קאזיל ואתי? ha
ka'azil ve'atei? The branches will go higher than three טפחים tefachim with
a little bit of wind. So, הגמרא haGemara says הכא נמי דאבדיה
בהוצא ודפנא. hacha nami de'avdye behutza vedafna. Yes, fine, you tied it
down. אי הכי, ei hachi, מטלטל בכולה? metaltel bekulah? If that's true,
if you did it, then it in the end it was made
by human hands, you know, it became a full מחיצה mechitza by
human hands. So then there should be no, you should be able
to carry in it no matter how big it is. Why and
how do we know you
can't?
דעלמה אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, de'almah amar Rav Huna breih
deRav Yehoshua, why does Rav Huna the son of Rav Yehoshua say,
אין מטלטלין בו אלא בית סאתים? ein metaltelin bo ela beit satayim?
So this will remind you of all the fun about עירובין. Eruvin.
A בית סאתים beit satayim is 50 אמות amot by 50
אמות, amot, no I'm sorry, 50 אמות amot by 100 אמות. amot.
It's 5000 square אמות. amot. And the basic idea of a בית
סאתים beit satayim is the following is that if something is not
a full מחיצה, mechitza, I mean, it is מחיצה, mechitza, but for
example, a classic example is that it's not עשוי בידי אדם, asuy
biyadei adam, it's a natural מחיצה, mechitza, it's not made by humans.
So, you know what, that's an imprecise way of saying it. The
idea is like this: if the area is not considered הוקף לדירה.
hukaf ledira. If the area, yes, is surrounded by walls, but it's
not surrounded for the purpose of habitation. There's a fence around it,
there's a wall around it, but somehow it was done for other
purposes other than habitation. Let's say, for example, you put a fence
around a forest to keep out intruders. You're not making it so
that anybody lives in it, you're just trying to keep people out.
So an area that's not הוקף לדירה, hukaf ledira, you cannot carry
in, if it's not considered rabbinically a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid if
it's bigger than בית סאתים, beit satayim, if it's bigger than 5000
square אמות. amot. So, הגמרא haGemara says, if this was completely made
naturally, totally by the tree, I understand why you can't carry if
it's bigger than בית סאתים. beit satayim. It's not הוקף לדירה, hukaf
ledira, completely natural. No human being ever surrounded the area. area for
the purpose of habitation. But if you're saying that you tied down
the branches, then you made it, then it was made by a
human, and then it should be made for the purpose of habitation.
And then, there should not be any limit in terms of how
long, how big it can be, that you can still consider it
a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. Okay. So why is it that there
is a limit if it's being made by a human, it's considered
made for habitation? So the גמרא Gemara says משום דהוי mishum dehavi
there's a different reason. Yes, it's made by humans, but still it's
not based, it's not הוקף לדירה. hukaf ledira. Why not? משום דהוי
דירה דתשמישה לאוויר. mishum dehavi dira detashmisheih la'avir. It's made for the
air. וכל דירה דתשמישה לאוויר אין מטלטלין בו אלא בית סאתיים. vechol
dira detashmisheih la'avir ein metalpelin bo ela beit satayim. And that's also
you can't carry if it's bigger than בית סאתיים. beit satayim. Now
what does it mean it's made for the air? So רש"י Rashi
says, why would people like, you know, sort of go under this
tree and want there to be wall, like use the tree as
walls? So רש"י Rashi imagine you're out there in the in the
forest and you're watching your sheep or you're watching, you know, the
crop and you want to take refuge underneath this tree. So not
on שבת, Shabbat, generally. Okay. So the purpose is not that you
want to be in it for the sake of being in it,
you want to be in it in order to be watching what's
going on outside of it. And that according to רש"י Rashi is
called תשמישה לאוויר. tashmisheih la'avir. I know, you're making a face. You
know, like, so I don't understand, so like if you made a
guardhouse would that be תשמישה לאוויר tashmisheih la'avir because you're watching what's
going on outside? Anyway. So the answer is, yes, it's made by
humans, yes, it's made to live under it, but it's still at
some level not considered הוקף לדירה hukaf ledira because it's made fundamentally
for the area outside. Okay. But anyway we had to say that
because the easier answer is it wasn't made by humans and it's
totally natural and then obviously it's not made for the purpose of
habitation and that's why it would have the limit. Let's do one
more case, let's finish to the משנה. Mishna. תא שמע,
tashma,
שבת בתל, Shabbat betel, if somebody
began שבת, Shabbat, this is so on one issue of מחיצה mechitzah
is it a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid can you carry in it.
The other issue of a מחיצה mechitzah is if you're inside of
a house, you know you measure two thousand אמות amot in every
direction, right? So if you're inside of a house, you measure the
two thousand אמות amot from the edges of the house, right? You
don't measure it from where you're standing. So if you're in a
רשות היחיד reshut hayachid then if we consider the space you're in
a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid the two thousand אמות amot starts from
the edges of that space. If we don't, it starts from you.
So this is another important discussion of is this a רשות היחיד
reshut hayachid or not. Okay. So you started שבת Shabbat on top
of a mound, גבוה עשרה, gavo'ah asarah, it's ten טפחים tefachim high,
ומארבע אמות עד בית סאתיים ume'arba amot ad beit satayim and it's
from four אמות amot to two a בית סאתיים. beit satayim. So
that's going to be a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid because you use
the edges of the rock to be considered virtual walls. But again,
only בית סאתיים. beit satayim. More than בית סאתיים beit satayim because
it's natural it is you know not considered a
רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. וכן בניקא vechen benika or similarly a crevice
שהוא עמוק עשרה shehu amok asarah that's deep ten, ומארבע אמות עד
בית סאתיים. ume'arba amot ad beit satayim. וכן קמה קצורה vechen kamah
ketzurah or if you're in the middle of cut wheat, right? ושיבולים
מקיפות אותו veshibbolim makkifot oto and you have bundles of wheat surrounding
you. מהלך את כולה וחוץ לה אלפיים אמה. mehallich et kullah vechutz
lah alpaim amah. All of this is רשות היחיד reshut hayachid and
you can go the entire space and two thousand אמות amot from
the outer limit. So the גמרא Gemara who says אע"ג דאזל ואתי,
afgav de'azal ve'atei, oh look it's blowing and it's moving? So it
says דקטרנהו במיחתא והדיב במיחתא. dekatarnehu bemichta vehadiv bemichta. You bound that
down as well, you tied that down as well. So a lot
of אוקימתות okimtot but in the end this becomes the issue that
bothers people about the about the canvas סוכות Sukkot which is why
they now have these straps so that even if the canvas billows
the you know the wall is still created through this whole idea
of לבוד. luvud. All righty. יישר כח. Yasher koach. Yep.
So I'm sorry yeah we got she got home late. Is this
about the cast? Oh that's exciting.
So yes it's confirmed it's confirmed with her.
Oh great so I will let her know. So what's so far
when?
Sunday between twelve and
two. Yeah with all the supplies.
Okay it's exciting I'll let her know it's going to be a
surprise for her.
Yeah.